<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two essays sent in a letter from Oxford to a nobleman in London the first concerning some errors about the creation, general flood, and the peopling of the world : in two parts : the second concerning the rise, progress, and destruction of fables and romances, with the state of learning / by L.P., Master of Arts.</title>
            <author>L. P., Master of Arts.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P77</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12952638</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12952638</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96000</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96000)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 363:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two essays sent in a letter from Oxford to a nobleman in London the first concerning some errors about the creation, general flood, and the peopling of the world : in two parts : the second concerning the rise, progress, and destruction of fables and romances, with the state of learning / by L.P., Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>L. P., Master of Arts.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], v, 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: filmed copy difficult to read due to foxing.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96000:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96000:1"/>
            <p>TWO ESSAYS SENT IN A LETTER from <hi>Oxford,</hi> TO A Nobleman in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt concerning ſome Errors about the Creation, General Flood, and the Peopling of the World. <hi>In Two Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second concerning the Riſe, Progreſs, and Deſtruction of Fables and Romances. With the State of Learning.</p>
            <p>By <hi>L. P.</hi> Maſter of Arts.</p>
            <q>Edita Doctrinâ Sapientum Templa Serena. <bibl>
                  <hi>Lucret. Lib. 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:96000:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:96000:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY For Writing the Following ESSAYS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE univerſal diſpoſition of this Age is bent upon a Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Religion; the fierceneſs of <hi>Bigotry</hi> is in good meaſure calm'd and allay'd; therefore I venture out upon this Pacifick Sea, hoping to reach my Port without any ſtorm or hardſhip. Moſt Nations in <hi>Europe</hi> allow of a Liberty and Latitude in Natural Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy; <hi>Copernicus, Galileo, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panella, Merſennus, Gaſſendus,
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:96000:3"/>Carteſius,</hi> and many others, are not eſteem'd the worſe Chriſtians, becauſe they contradict the Scriptures in Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Mathematical Problems; the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Writers</hi> ſpoke to a Generation of Men, who were never famous in Arts and Sciences; therefore they adapted all their ſayings to the vulgar Idea's of that Time and Nation; their deſign being not to compoſe a Natural ſyſtem of the World, but to eſtabliſh the true <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy,</hi> and good <hi>Morals.</hi> What un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Calumnies have been thrown upon the <hi>Worthy Maſter of the Charter-Houſe,</hi> upon the account of his <hi>Theory of the Earth,</hi> and his <hi>Archaeologia,</hi> (Pieces of admirable Workmanſhip) which his Enemies may be aſham'd of, as ſome were upon the diſcovery of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes</hi> and the <hi>New World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Philoſophick Hiſtory of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> is not always to be embraced; for what an outcry againſt Mr. <hi>Hobs!</hi>
               <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:96000:3"/>becauſe he deſcrib'd God Almighty as Corporeal, though <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> had done ſo before him. Things are denominated <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> not by any certain Rules of Truth, or Falſhood, but according to the Caprice, or Intereſts of <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Parties:</hi> So the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were called <hi>Athei</hi> by the <hi>Pagans,</hi> becauſe they did not Sacrifice, nor conſult Oracles, nor Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Images: So one Nation calls ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Barbarous, becauſe different in Habit, Manners, Diet, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. The Philoſophers of <hi>Athens</hi> ſtiled one another <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as they frequented ſuch a <hi>School,</hi> or <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> ſo in <hi>England</hi> we give <hi>Nick-Names,</hi> according to the Company we keep, or the Books we read, or as we va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in our Dreams, or Idea's, or in our Deſigns. <hi>Non omnes, probè no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, veritatem metiuntur aut eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant rationum pondere &amp; momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſed affectibus abrepti aut pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicijs
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:96000:4"/>occaecati, quaſi clauſis Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, de rerum coloribus decernunt. Saepe etiam ad concitandam invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Authoris mentem aut verba in alienas partes detorquent. Haec Signa homines ſolent variè inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretari, &amp; trahere ad ſua vota, aut ſpes, aut metus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So, <hi>My Lord,</hi> I will conclude this <hi>Apology,</hi> which I thought neceſſary to premiſe in order to level the way to a fair reception and interpretation of theſe Eſſays, which come from one, whom your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> knows to be well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and not in the leaſt tinctur'd with <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> a crime unjuſtly charg'd upon many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Men, who have a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Zeal and Veneration for the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, All-Wiſe, and All-Powerful Being.</hi> I have Travell'd many Countries, yet could never meet with any <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> which are few, if any; all the noiſe and
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:96000:4"/>clamour is againſt Caſtles in the Air; a ſort of War, like that of <hi>Don Quixotte,</hi> with the Windmills. So I take my leave, and farewell; being,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's Moſt Devoted Servant, <hi>L. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:96000:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96000:5"/>
            <head>THE FIRST ESSAY, CONCERNING Some Errors about the Firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, General Flood, and the Peopling of the World.</head>
            <head type="sub">In Two Parts.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Firſt PART.</head>
               <p>THE common Hiſtory of the firſt <hi>Chaos,</hi> of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal <hi>Deluge,</hi> and of the Peopling of the Old and New <hi>World,</hi> is ſo well known to every body, that any Account of them in this place will ſeem unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; eſpecially to you who has read ſo many excellent Writers upon them, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96000:6"/>
                  <hi>Judge Hales</hi> of the <hi>Origination of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; Dr. Burnet's moſt ingenious Theory; Mr. Ray's Three Phyſico-Theological Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore I will confine my ſelf, in this ſhort Eſſay, to a plain Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of matter of Fact, as it ſtands in Nature, and as it appears to our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; which, I know, will pleaſe you beſt, who long ago began to deride <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes,</hi> and monſtrous <hi>Traditions,</hi> invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and inſtill'd in Cells, in Nurſeries, or in Schools, the fountains of <hi>Mythology;</hi> which hath in all Ages infected the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Nature with <hi>Fables, Chimera's,</hi> and <hi>Romances;</hi> and even to that degree, that God Almighty himſelf (Bleſſed for ever) muſt be made uſe of upon all occaſions to invert and confound his own ſettled Order of Cauſes, and to commit abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities in Nature, either to make good an uncertain Tradition, or to corroborate a vain Fancy. <hi>Non ſunt ij aut ſcientiâ aut Arte divini, ſed ſuperſtitioſi vates, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudenteſque Harioli, aut inertes aut inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, aut quibus Egeſtas imperat; Qui ſibi ſemitam non ſapiunt, alteri monſtrant Viam.</hi> Cicero de Divinatio.</p>
               <p>But to come cloſe to the Point: We have been told of old, That at the firſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96000:6"/>Creation all was mingled in a fluid <hi>Chaos;</hi> and that in proceſs of time there came on gradual Separations, Sediments, and that concreted <hi>Maſs,</hi> which we now call the <hi>World.</hi> This made ſome great <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Ray</hi>'s Three Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſico-Theol. Diſcourſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> conclude, That the Shells, Teeth, and other Bones of Fiſhes, were embowel'd in the Beds, or Strata of the Earth, upon the gradual, or leiſurely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, or draining of the Waters after the Firſt <hi>Creation.</hi> We have alſo been aſſur'd, that theſe Shells, and Bones, and Plants, were diſperſed all the Earth over, and lodged deep in its Bowels, in Beds, or Strata, at the Univerſal <hi>Deluge</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Steno's Prodro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, <hi>Tranſlated by Mr.</hi> Ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg. <hi>Dr.</hi> Hooks Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crograph. Ray's Travels, <hi>from p.</hi> 113. <hi>to p.</hi> 130. Plot <hi>of</hi> Oxfordſhire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>: But how far either of theſe Opinions, or Hypotheſes, will ſtand an ordinary Teſt, you will ſoon judge, after your wonted manner, Phyſically, Mechanically, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally; for I know you rely no further upon <hi>Authority,</hi> than as it is agreeable to common Senſe, or to the ordinary <hi>Providence</hi> of God Almighty.</p>
               <p>The moſt rational way to examine theſe <hi>Problems,</hi> is by the Laws of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> or by the <hi>Hydroſtaticks;</hi> becauſe the Controverſie is about the deſcent of <hi>Solids</hi> in <hi>Fluids;</hi> in the managing of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96000:7"/>which there is no need of any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or Miraculous intervention of the firſt <hi>Infinite Cauſe,</hi> the principles and rules being originally eſtabliſhed by it; and though we may grant that the firſt <hi>Chaos</hi> and the univerſal <hi>Flood</hi> might be miraculouſly brought about; yet there is no colour for thinking that the Hand of <hi>God</hi> would confound it's own <hi>Laws</hi> (where there was no manner of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity) in forming and reforming the <hi>Machine</hi> we call the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of <hi>Gravity,</hi> for ſettling this <hi>Terraqueous Globe</hi> of ours, in the Figure and Texture we now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe then all the <hi>Solids</hi> diſſolv'd, or intermixt, floating and ſubſiding in the great <hi>Fluid</hi> of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> or in the vaſt <hi>Abyſs</hi> of the <hi>Deluge;</hi> the moſt ponderous muſt ſubſide firſt, deepeſt, or neareſt the Center; and the reſt according to their ſeveral reſpective weights, or ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick gravities muſt take their places in this new <hi>Bed,</hi> or <hi>Maſs of Sediments.</hi> The <hi>Metals</hi> would be the loweſt, the reſt of the <hi>Foſſils</hi> above them, the <hi>Abyſs</hi> of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter above theſe, and ſo on to the <hi>Animal</hi> and <hi>Vegetable Bodies;</hi> which could not <hi>Statically</hi> ſubſide with parts heavier in Bulk, or in Specie.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96000:7"/>
               <p>But let us view theſe <hi>Layers,</hi> or <hi>Strata</hi> of the <hi>Globe,</hi> as far as they appear to our Senſes. The <hi>Metals</hi> are often at the top, <hi>Beds</hi> of <hi>Marble</hi> near the ſuperficies, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, Teſtaceous and other Animal-like Bodies</hi> lower ſtill; and the <hi>Abyſs,</hi> or ſphere of Water ſaid to be loweſt of all; an odd face of <hi>Sediments,</hi> a fantaſtical deſcent of <hi>Solids</hi> in a <hi>Fluid;</hi> neither Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, nor Preternatural, nor Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, without Deſign, or any End.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the ſame Shells, and Marine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Bodies, are not only found deep in <hi>Beds</hi> of Earth and Stone, of different ſpecifick Gravity; but alſo on the very <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of the Earth it ſelf, as <hi>Cockles,</hi> and <hi>Cornua Ammonis</hi> (the moſt ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous) under which are ſeveral <hi>Layers</hi> of Earth lighter than they; if the latter <hi>(viz. Cornu Ammonis)</hi> is any <hi>Species</hi> of Teſtaceous Animal, it is either not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant at this day, or elſe lies deep in the bottom of the Sea remote from the Shoars; where 'tis hard to conceive <hi>Broods</hi> of ſuch Shell-fiſh, where there is ſuch want of Air, of Food, and ſuch a mighty preſſure of Water, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſqueeze and break much firmer Bodies.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96000:8"/>
               <p>But perhaps the Water might be ſo kind as to diſſever<note n="*" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>'s late Eſſay.</note>, or take to pieces the <hi>Adamantine Rocks, Porphyry,</hi> and <hi>Talc</hi> (inſuperable to fire, and to moſt Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Art) and to preſerve at the ſame time her brittle Shells, and the tender Plants entire and whole, whilſt the ſtubborn Maſs of <hi>Foſſils</hi> was forc'd to yeild and lye diſſolv'd in a furious <hi>Abyſs;</hi> this may paſs with <hi>Romantick</hi> Readers, but ſcarce with any ſound or thinking <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis hard to conceive how Leaves, and light Shells ſhould fall in <hi>Aequilibrio</hi> with the much heavier parts of <hi>Marbles, Minerals,</hi> and other <hi>Foſſils,</hi> and be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied with them in the ſame Beds, Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or <hi>Strata,</hi> by the Principles of the ſame ſpecifick <hi>Gravity,</hi> whoſe <hi>Laws</hi> are certain and conſtant. Crab's and Lob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's claws, and all light Shells whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, are ſaid very ſeldom to occur upon Land; becauſe being left on the ſurface of the Earth after the <hi>Deluge,</hi> and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Air, and other accidents, they were rotted and deſtroyed (<hi>Dr.</hi> Woodward <hi>in his Eſſay</hi>). To which 'tis anſwered, That the lighteſt Shells on our Shoars, are the <hi>Echini;</hi> yet the <hi>Echinites</hi> of divers kinds or ſorts (with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96000:8"/>reſpect to the number of Shells on our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Coaſts) are the moſt common <hi>Foſſil Shells,</hi> or <hi>Shell-ſtones</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and they are often found at the depth of at leaſt Three or Four Fathom, and that under Rocks of ſolid Stone; and as for joints of <hi>Crab's Claws,</hi> they have been found lodged about Six Fathom deep, upon the ſinking of a Well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coral,</hi> and the <hi>Aſtroites <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndulatus,</hi> or the <hi>Sea-Muſhroom,</hi> are ſometimes found ſticking to theſe ſuppoſed <hi>Anti-deluvian Shells.</hi> Which is an Argument that the whole <hi>Mineral</hi> Kingdom (of which theſe are properly <hi>Members</hi>) was not diſſolv'd in the <hi>Hodg-Podg,</hi> or <hi>Pudding</hi> of the <hi>Deluge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Author of the late Eſſay</hi> cenſures Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> for broaching and vending Opinions contrary to the ſenſe of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture;</hi> yet he himſelf will be found to contradict the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Moſes:</hi> For whereas he gathers from his <hi>Anti-deluvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> Plants, that the Earth was not only totally drowned, but alſo diſſolved ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time betwixt the 17th of <hi>May,</hi> and the end of the ſame Month; <hi>Moſes</hi> tells us the Waters prevailed (<hi>i. e.</hi> as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, the Flood increaſed) for 150 days, ere the <hi>Fountains</hi> of the <hi>Deep</hi> were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96000:9"/>ſhut up; nor was it neceſſary, in caſe the <hi>World</hi> was diſſolved in a Fortnight's ſpace, that it ſhould Rain 40 days and 40 nights for the drowning of it. But 'tis no wonder to ſee <hi>Phyſical Theoriſts,</hi> and <hi>Hypothetical Speculators,</hi> grope and ſtumble in the dark, as ſooon as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to deſert the day-light of Senſe, and to float out of all depth.</p>
               <p>Upon enquiries made into the bottom of the Sea by <hi>Divers,</hi> and <hi>Navigators,</hi> it appears to conſiſt of inequalities of <hi>Rocks, Mountains, Valleys, Beds</hi> of Sand and Earth, of <hi>Foſſils</hi> and <hi>Plants,</hi> though of different kinds from thoſe at <hi>Land.</hi> In this Aqueous part of the <hi>Globe,</hi> the Water is uppermoſt, whereas in the other 'tis lowermoſt; an Argument that the manner of the ſubſiding (or deſcent in the general <hi>Fluid</hi> at the <hi>Chaos,</hi> or <hi>Flood</hi>) of <hi>Solid Bodies,</hi> was quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in theſe two parts of the <hi>Globe,</hi> and therefore not proceeding from the ſame Cauſes or Principles; whereas Nature is uniform in all her parts, and <hi>Providence</hi> Beautiful in her Symmetry.</p>
               <p>To conclude therefore the Firſt Part of this <hi>Eſſay;</hi> I cannot but continue in my old Opinion, That the <hi>World</hi> was thus form'd from the Beginning, no total
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96000:9"/>
                  <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> nor any univerſal <hi>Inundation:</hi> Some particular great Changes have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, as new Mountains by turning up of the Earth; ſome new <hi>Iſlands,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at the Mouths of great Rivers, by their Sediments of Earth brought down from the Land; ſome new Lakes by <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> and ſome other Mutations from particular <hi>Floods,</hi> or <hi>Vulcano</hi>'s; though a late Author will ſcarce allow of any of theſe ſorts<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> in his Eſſay.</note>; nothing but a <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſſolution of the whole Terreſtrial Globe</hi> will go down with him; the ſmaller Changes by Earthquakes not paſſing currant; though <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of Senſe make for the latter, and only Dreams and Phantomes for the former.</p>
               <p>All theſe Marine-like Bodies digg'd out of the Bowels of the Earth, may, with more appearance of Reaſon, be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar ſorts of <hi>Foſſils,</hi> (as an <hi>Ingenious Writer ſuppoſes</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Liſter <hi>in</hi> Tranſact. Philoſoph. <hi>and</hi> de Cochlit.</note>) or Natives, or Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Creatures of the Earth, (call them what you pleaſe) rather than Strangers, brought in by I know not what barbarous <hi>Inundations,</hi> and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Diſſolutions, and ſettled there by I know not what Laws, or Force, or Power; I am confident not by any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96000:10"/>
                  <hi>Divine Appointment,</hi> for that acts more regularly, and more diſcretely.</p>
               <p>I would gladly know why theſe <hi>Shell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Bodies,</hi> or <hi>Plant-like Subſtances,</hi> may not be Congenial to the Earth. Plants will propagate on Land, and in Water, withont any viſible or manifeſt Seed; Shells will ſhoot, or grow in the Glands of Animals; and Infects may ſometimes breed without Animal Parents, or Eggs, or Seed; therefore why not Teſtaceous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Subſtances, or Shells themſelves in Beds of Earth, or Stone, where they are found; rather than be brought and laid there by <hi>Fairies,</hi> or <hi>inviſible Agents,</hi> that muſt turn Heaven and Earth up to make way for thoſe <hi>Toys,</hi> and preſerve them Miraculouſly in their <hi>Voyage</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               <p>Thus have I done with this <hi>Problem.</hi> If you pleaſe to ſtudy and know it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, you muſt conſult many Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: As,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fab. Columna de Purpur. &amp; Gloſſope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris,</hi> with <hi>Dan. Major</hi> his Notes. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> 
                  <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae.</hi> 1675.</p>
               <p>Hook<hi>'s Micrography,</hi> and <hi>Lectures</hi> upon <hi>Spring.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96000:10"/>
               <p>Steno<hi>'s Prodromus. Lat.</hi> and <hi>Eng.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi>.</p>
               <p>Steno <hi>de Cane Carchariâ &amp; Gloſſope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi>.</p>
               <p>Ray<hi>'s Topograph. Obſervations made in a Journey, &amp;c.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi>. From p. 113. to p. 131.</p>
               <p>Ray<hi>'s Three Phyſico-Theological Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp;c.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi>. Second Edition, 1693.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grandius</hi> and <hi>Quirinus de Diluvio <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali à Teſtaceis Foſſilibus. Venet.</hi> 1676. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agoſtino Scilla Letter a circa</hi> 1 <hi>Corpi Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini Petrificati.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> 
                  <hi>Con molte Figur. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli,</hi> 1670. As quoted by Mr. <hi>Ray,</hi> the Book being unknown to me.</p>
               <p>P. Boccone <hi>in his Recherches &amp; Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv. Nat.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi>. 1674.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Plot<hi>'s Natur. Hiſtor. of</hi> Oxford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Liſter <hi>in Philoſoph. Tranſact.</hi> and <hi>de Cochlitis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Woodward <hi>in his Eſſay toward a Natural Hiſtory of the Earth.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi>. 1695.</p>
               <p>All the aforegoing <hi>Authors,</hi> except Dr. <hi>Liſter,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Plot,</hi> ſtretch hard to fetch theſe <hi>Land Shells</hi> from the bottom of the <hi>Sea</hi> to the tops of <hi>Mountains,</hi> and into the deep entrails of the <hi>Earth,</hi> by the means of a <hi>Chaos,</hi> a <hi>Deluge,</hi> or <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes;</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96000:11"/>but all of them in different ways, and with what ſucceſs, I think, I have made clear.</p>
               <p>But now we are upon this Subject, let us diſcourſe a little with the <hi>Author</hi> of the late <hi>Eſſay toward a Natural Hiſtory of the Earth: Who ſays, p.</hi> 108. That the Teeth, Bones, and other Parts of Animal Bodies, as alſo the Trunks, Roots, and other Parts of Vegetables, were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in the Deluge, as all the Foſſils and Solids of the Earth were. Now if theſe Vegetable and Animal Parts of the Land floated entire and whole, Why do not we find greater quantities of them under ground? The <hi>Anti-diluvian</hi> Trees, and eſpecially the Bones of Terreſtrial living Creatures, would be more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully buried, or embodied under ground, than the remote Spoils of the Sea, which in ſome places muſt have Travelled Two or Three thouſand Miles to get into their Land-Beds, and that too in a very ſhort ſpace: The <hi>Author</hi> (<hi>Dr.</hi> Woodward <hi>in his Eſſay</hi>) allowing but ſome time in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> for bringing about this mighty <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Change;</hi> which if ſo quick, how will he bring together into one place ſo many diſtant and different Animals ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96000:11"/>of Miles over both Sea and Land? And the <hi>Author</hi> will have a pretty piece of work to convey all theſe <hi>Species</hi> of living Creatures back again to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective <hi>Continents</hi> and <hi>Iſlands,</hi> unleſs he keeps in Store all his Carriages, his Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, his Magazines, his Tranſport-Ships, and other Neceſſaries for long Marches and Navigations.</p>
               <p>I thought to have proceeded in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of his great <hi>Abyſs</hi> of Waters, and his Subterraneous Fire over them; as alſo of his Origin of Springs, Rivers, Vapours and Rain, and of his manner of forming Metals; but I refer thoſe Parts to abler Pens, who underſtand Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Calculation and Motions of Fluids, the Generation and Growth of Metals and other Foſſils: However, I will touch a little upon the manner of ſtocking his New <hi>Globe</hi> a Second time, after his <hi>great beloved Cataſtrophe;</hi> which he extends to all the Regions of <hi>Aſia, Africa, Europe,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> tho only Part of <hi>Meſopotomia</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> were Inhabited by the <hi>Anti-diluvians,</hi> upon whoſe account he will have this Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Diſſolution of the whole Globe of Earth to be brought on; which is not agreeable to the uſual methods of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96000:12"/>nor to the Wiſdom of the <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> for what deſign could there be in deſtroying all the innocent dumb Creatures, and the Beauty of the Creation, in the Uninhabited Parts (which were above a Hundred to One, in reſpect of thoſe Planted by the <hi>Anti-diluvian People</hi>) for the ſake only of a few Wanton and Luxurious <hi>Aſiaticks,</hi> who might have been drown'd by a <hi>Topi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Flood,</hi> or by a particular Deluge, without involving all the Bowels of the whole Maſs, and the remote Creatures upon the face of the Earth, in their Ruin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96000:12"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE Firſt ESSAY: CONCERNING The Peopling and Planting the New World, and other remote Countries.</head>
               <p>THE Deſign of this Second Part, is not to calumniate, or diminiſh the Authority of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who, without diſpute, was one of the Greateſt and Wiſeſt <hi>Legiſlators</hi> that ever appear'd in the World, not excepting <hi>Solon,</hi> or <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus,</hi> or <hi>Numa.</hi> He brought a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Idolatrous Nation, to the Worſhip of One <hi>True God,</hi> and eſtabliſhed many Excellent Laws amongſt them: He adapted his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Deluge</hi> to their Capacities; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can be no Crime in one, who is no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96000:13"/>
                  <hi>Jew,</hi> to Comment a little upon ſome parts of it, with a Chriſtian plainneſs, and a Philoſophical Liberty, founded upon <hi>Nature</hi> her ſelf.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and the vaſt <hi>Regions</hi> lately diſcovered towards the <hi>South,</hi> abound with ſuch variety of Inhabitants, and New Animals, not known or ever ſeen in <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>Europe,</hi> that the <hi>Origine</hi> of them doth not appear ſo clear as ſome late <hi>Writers</hi> pretend; eſpecially ſeeing there are no <hi>Records</hi> or <hi>Monuments</hi> of their <hi>Tranſmigrations</hi> out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> or any other known parts of the <hi>World,</hi> either before or after the <hi>Flood;</hi> and their differences from all the reſt of the <hi>Globe,</hi> in Manners, Languages, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, Religions, Diet, Arts, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, as well as in their Quadrupeds, Birds, Serpents, and Inſects, render their Derivation very obſcure, and their Origine uncertain, eſpecially in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way, and according to the vulgar Opinions of Planting all the Earth from one little Spot.</p>
               <p>The great Zeal to maintain a <hi>Jewiſh Tradition,</hi> put many Learned <hi>Chriſtians</hi> upon the rack to make it out. Every corner is ſearch'd to find out a Word, a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96000:13"/>Rite, or a Cuſtom, in order to derive from thence many Millions of different People. Some will have <hi>Norway,</hi> others <hi>Tartary</hi> and <hi>China,</hi> or ſome <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts of <hi>Africa,</hi> to be the Source and Seminary of <hi>Creatures,</hi> unknown and ſtrange to thoſe <hi>Climates.</hi> The <hi>Welchmen</hi> are not wanting in their Chimera's of Peopling <hi>Mexico</hi> with their <hi>Colonies;</hi> and perhaps they have better Authority than any can be produc'd for the reſt. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> becauſe they found ſome Sticks and pieces of Wood laid Croſs-ways, would needs have the <hi>Indians</hi> to be of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The <hi>Jews</hi> fancied the <hi>Americans</hi> to be Circumcis'd (their Prepuces being only eaten with the Pox) and therefore would have them to be of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Race: But we will examine the chief of theſe Opinions with brevity and perſpicuity.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Norway</hi> the Navigation is very difficult, even to our New ſtrong built Ships; the vaſt <hi>Iſlands</hi> of Ice, and the Weather in thoſe Seas muſt have been invincible to the little Boats or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of thoſe days; and the Journeys over Land through <hi>Greenland</hi> are impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by reaſon of the Mountains and Rocks of Ice and Snow; beſides there is a great difference in the Colour, Numbers, in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96000:14"/>the Cuſtoms, and Mechanicks of the Natives of <hi>Canada, New England, Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> &amp;c. and of the <hi>Norwegians;</hi> no foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to be found amongſt the Northern <hi>Indians,</hi> which are ſaid to Tranſmigrate in the Ninth or Tenth Century. All Nations agree in ſome Words, and in ſome Cuſtoms; therefore a reſemblance in a few of them is no proof. But further, <hi>John de Laet</hi> aſſures us, That with great diligence he found a <hi>Mexican Dictionary,</hi> but could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferve any Words to agree with any <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean</hi> Language. Beſides, many <hi>Writers</hi> who reſided a long time in the <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> affirm, that there are ſo many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Languages and Dialects in the ſame Kingdom, that one Province doth not underſtand another, even in <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Braſil;</hi> and along the banks of the ſingle River of <hi>Amazons</hi> there are above One hundred and ſixty different Tongues and Nations, compos'd of infinite numbers of various People; ſo that this Country, with <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Mexico,</hi> might contend with any in <hi>Aſia,</hi> not only in their Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, but in their Manufactures, and Mechanicks, as well as in their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Governments; and they might with the ſame reaſon boaſt of their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96000:14"/>giving Birth to us, as we to them.</p>
               <p>The Origine of moſt, if not of all Nations, is wrapt up in fabulous Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Records and Monuments are of late dates; and when we offer at the beginnings of things, we are ſwallowed up and loſt in the darkneſs and depth of time. Arts, Inventions, and many other things might be loſt in the Univerſal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtations of Countries, and ſometimes reviv'd again in Revolutions.</p>
               <p>The Paſſage from <hi>Tartary</hi> into <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> is as obſcure as that from <hi>Norway,</hi> and the ſame difficulties lye againſt it; the ſtretching of the <hi>Tartarian Capes</hi> are unknown; but if they ſhould be join'd to the back of <hi>Northern America,</hi> the Journey would be very dangerous (if not impoſſible) to <hi>Colonies.</hi> The <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> abound more with Horſes than all the World beſides, and cannot ſubſiſt without them; therefore it is very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable they ſhould ſwarm into <hi>America</hi> on foot (when they ride in all other parts) and their Offſpring ſhould be ſo affrighted with the ſight of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Horſe, that a 1000 <hi>Tartar-Indians</hi> ſhould run away from a ſingle Mounted <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier.</hi> The Land in <hi>Tartary,</hi> ſaid to be the high Road for this Tranſmigration
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96000:15"/>out of the <hi>Old</hi> into the <hi>New World,</hi> runs further <hi>North</hi> than <hi>Nova Zembla,</hi> or <hi>Greenland;</hi> and how the Animals, that cannot endure the extremity of Cold, ſhould climb over inacceſſible Mountains of Ice and Snow for many Thouſands of Miles together, is hardly explicable to any thinking man; and that thoſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that live in the Frozen Continent, ſhould not be able to Travel along with tender Strangers, and delicate Paſſengers, is ſcarce credible; Horſes, Ermines, and Sables (that abound in <hi>Tartary</hi>) might have found a way much more eaſily than <hi>Indian Creatures.</hi> A man muſt preſs hard to ſtrain <hi>Braſil, Peru,</hi> and <hi>Mexico,</hi> through frozen Seas, or congeal'd Deſarts, made up of Snow from the beginning, and cover'd with Night for half the year.</p>
               <p>Neither is it probable that either <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegians, Laplanders, Muſcovites, Tartars,</hi> or the <hi>People of Jeſſe,</hi> ſhould carry along with them Ravenous Beaſts, or Venom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Serpents, or ſuch Animals, as never flock into their Countries, as <hi>Lyons, Tygers, Alligators, Monkeys, Apes, Parrots,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Navigations from <hi>China</hi> through the <hi>South</hi> Sea to <hi>America,</hi> are impoſſible to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96000:15"/>the <hi>Jonks</hi> of that Kingdom, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not carry Proviſions for long Voyages; beſides, the <hi>Northern</hi> Parts of the <hi>South</hi> Seas are too high for them, and the Trade-winds always contrary at <hi>Eaſt</hi> in the <hi>Latitudes of Peru</hi> and <hi>Mexico.</hi> The Compaſs (neceſſary in ſuch ſorts of Sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by long Sea) could not be known to the <hi>Chineſes</hi> in thoſe Ages; beſides, the Language of <hi>China</hi> conſiſts all of <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyllables,</hi> whereas thoſe of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru</hi> have many. The <hi>Indians</hi> knew nothing of Style, Pen, Ink, Paper, or any manner of Writing (ſo common in the <hi>Eaſt</hi>) but reckoned the Antiquity of Time by ſtrung Beads, Knots, and Pebbles: They had neither Bellows, Saws, nor Nails, though plenty of Iron Oar in the Country; but they knew not the way of ſeparating, ſo long practiſed in the <hi>Old World,</hi> before their traditional paſſage out of it.</p>
               <p>From the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Coaſts of <hi>Africa,</hi> the Sailing is more eaſy, but then the Natives are moſt <hi>Negroes,</hi> or much blacker than the <hi>Americans,</hi> who have long Hair, little or no Beards, and are of an Olive Colour.</p>
               <p>But to come cloſer to the matter; the <hi>Americans</hi> had neither Horſe, nor our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96000:16"/>ſort of Cow, Sheep, nor our barking Dogs, nor knew the uſe of Iron: 'Tis wonderful they ſhould carry ſo many fierce and deſtructive Creatures along with them, and leave the mild and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ones behind; but more wonderful they ſhould exhauſt the <hi>Old World</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Species</hi> of <hi>Animals,</hi> never found in it ſince (nor perhaps before) their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally-believed <hi>Tranſmigration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Twill be hard to make any man (mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately vers'd in the Hiſtory of Nature) confeſs, that the <hi>Pacos,</hi> or <hi>Glama</hi> of <hi>Peru,</hi> or that the <hi>Manati</hi> (a biped Animal) or many other Creatures peculiar to the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> ſhould Travel from <hi>Aſia</hi> (where they never were obſerv'd to exiſt) by I know not what ways into a ſtrange World, and all to ſupport an Old <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Tradition.</p>
               <p>'Tis unaccountable that the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed Beaſt, commonly called the <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus</hi> or <hi>Sluggard</hi> (that lives moſt upon Trees, and cannot march above Fourty or Sixty Yards in a day) ſhould get into <hi>America</hi> from <hi>Aſia,</hi> where no man ever ſaw it; and that neither <hi>Jacals</hi> nor <hi>Musk Deer</hi> (nimble vagabond Creatures) nor <hi>Rhinocerots,</hi> nor <hi>Elephants,</hi> nor <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels</hi> (Itinerant Animals) ſhould ever
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96000:16"/>ſlip over into the New World by the ſame paths or ways that the others went, which have leſt none of their Kind behind them.</p>
               <p>But then ſuppoſe that <hi>America</hi> was ſtock'd ſome time or other (in the days of <hi>King Arthur</hi>) from <hi>Norway, Tartary China, Land</hi> of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> or <hi>Africa;</hi> yet how came thoſe Myriads of People and new Animals (perhaps ſtrangers not only to the <hi>Old World,</hi> but to the New it ſelf) into thoſe immenſe <hi>Countries, South Weſt</hi> and <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> of <hi>America,</hi> diſcovered more lately by <hi>Ferdinando Quir, Van Diemen, Taſman,</hi> and others? The <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Canoes</hi> could not tranſport them over ſuch boyſterous long Seas; and the <hi>Lands</hi> about the <hi>Straits of Magellan</hi> are ſo deſart, that they could not afford ſuch mighty <hi>Colonies;</hi> neither can we fetch them from the Capes of <hi>Africa</hi> or <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee no way at preſent to ſolve this new face of <hi>Nature</hi> by old Arguments fetch'd from <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Rubbiſh, or Rabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Weeds, unleſs ſome <hi>New Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> ſtarts up with a freſh Syſtem; in the mean time let them all be <hi>Aborigines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some object, that <hi>America</hi> in former times was join'd to <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> by large necks of Land of eaſy paſſage,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96000:17"/>which were afterwards broke off by Earthquakes, Storms, or Inundations; but this is begging of the Queſtîon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of proof; ſuppoſe the fact was ſo, yet it gives no tolerable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count why the <hi>Animals</hi> of the <hi>New World</hi> ſhould differ in <hi>Specie</hi> from thoſe of the <hi>Old;</hi> and the <hi>Americans</hi> themſelves may with the ſame probability affirm, that they planted <hi>Aſia</hi> by theſe ways, ſeeing they were equally, if not more populous, and excelling in Morality, and Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Arts: For the firſt <hi>Spaniſh Writers</hi> tell us, they were amaz'd at the ſineneſs and contrivances of the <hi>Indian Works,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially their Artificers in Golden and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Wares, their Spinnings, and Weavings, and Joinery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for which <hi>Benzo,</hi> and <hi>Garcilaſſo de la Vega</hi> may be conſulted.</p>
               <p>But we will give all the rope and ſcope imaginable to the <hi>Moſaick Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi>'s calling all the Animals together, and naming them, and after wards <hi>Noah</hi>'s taking every <hi>Species</hi> of them into the <hi>Ark</hi> to preſerve them in the <hi>Deluge;</hi> yet their diſperſion into <hi>America,</hi> and the <hi>Terra Auſtralis</hi> by unknown paſſages, will ſcarce ſolve the difficulties in ſtocking the <hi>remote Iſlands</hi> with men and other living Creatures above a Thouſand
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96000:17"/>Leagues diſtant from any Land, as the <hi>Azores, Bermuda</hi>'s, the <hi>Iſles of the South Sea,</hi> &amp;c. moſt of which abound with Natives, Quadrupeds, Birds, and Inſects, different in Specie from thoſe of the next <hi>Continents,</hi> or <hi>Terra Firma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Learned <hi>Writer</hi> urges, That the <hi>Americans</hi> could be of no long ſtanding there, becauſe the <hi>Mexicans</hi> and <hi>Peruvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> could give no account of their being there above a Thouſand Years before the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion,</hi> which is a very ſtrong argument againſt himſelf, conſidering they had not the uſe of Letters (which methinks they might have brought with them from the <hi>Old World</hi>) nor <hi>Cyphers,</hi> nor any way of Regiſtring, but by Beads, or Stones. Beſides, ſeveral <hi>European</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can give no account of themſelves for the firſt Four Thouſand Years; What know we of <hi>Britain</hi> befote <hi>Julius Caeſar?</hi> or of <hi>Greece</hi> it ſelf before the <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan War?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not ignorant that ſome late <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> will have the <hi>New Animals</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> either to be Generated equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally there, or elſe to proceed from va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious mixtures of <hi>Animals</hi> ſent from hence; but this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, even to our own
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96000:18"/>
                  <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Old World,</hi> and may evert the <hi>Moſaick Syſtem</hi> here at home; for if there are equivocal Generations (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the moſt perfect Kinds) or new Species produced every day, What need of a ſetled uniform Creation, and ſuch a diſtinct Number of every <hi>Species</hi> of <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> or in <hi>Noah</hi>'s <hi>Ark?</hi> But beſides, equivocal Generations do not only tend to <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> but are evidently exploded by demonſtrative Experiments; and as to promiſcuous Generations (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call'd <hi>Hebridous</hi>) between diſtinct Kinds, they can never Propagate, as we ſee in <hi>Mules,</hi> &amp;c. and 'tis eaſily prov'd that there can be no Propagation of any new <hi>Species,</hi> but that the Number of Creatures, as to their Kinds, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been the ſame from the Beginning.</p>
               <p>As many difficulties lye againſt the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Syſtem of confining all <hi>Species</hi> of living Terreſtrial Creatures within the <hi>Aſiatick</hi> or Primaeval Paradiſe, and afterwards to <hi>Noah</hi>'s <hi>Ark;</hi> ſo more ſeem to ariſe againſt the Propagation of all <hi>Mankind</hi> out of one Single Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, unleſs all Poſterity, both <hi>Blacks</hi> and <hi>Whites,</hi> ſeparated by vaſt Seas, were all included actually in form within <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96000:18"/>
               <p>The Origin of <hi>Negroes</hi> lies very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, for time out of mind there hath been <hi>Blacks</hi> with a Woolly ſubſtance on their Bodies inſtead of Hair, becauſe they are mentioned in the moſt Ancient Records now extant in the World. 'Tis plain their Colour and Wool are Innate, or Seminal from their firſt beginning, and ſeems to be a Specifick Character, which neither the Sun, nor any Curſe from <hi>Cham</hi> could imprint upon them.</p>
               <p>Not the Firſt, becauſe many other <hi>Nations</hi> living under the ſame <hi>Climates</hi> and Heats, are never <hi>Black,</hi> as the <hi>Abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes,</hi> the <hi>Siamites,</hi> the <hi>Braſilians, Peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vians,</hi> &amp;c. neither will any <hi>White</hi> ever become a <hi>Black</hi> in <hi>Guinea, Congo,</hi> or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gola,</hi> though born there; neither will any <hi>Negroes</hi> produce <hi>Whites</hi> in <hi>Virginia,</hi> or <hi>New England.</hi> The Textures of their Skins, and Blood, differ from thoſe of <hi>Whites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not the Latter: For what Curſe is change of Colour, that being only acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental to Beauty, which conſiſts wholly in Proportion and Symmetry? The Old <hi>Statues</hi> in Black Marble, are as much, if not more, valued than thoſe in White. Beſides, the Curſe upon <hi>Cham</hi>'s account muſt have turn'd many of the <hi>Aſiaticks,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96000:19"/>and all the <hi>Egyptians</hi> into <hi>Negroes;</hi> for they were Curs'd more peculiarly than the <hi>Weſtern</hi> remote Coaſts of <hi>Africa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Colour (which appears to be as Ingenite, and as Original as that in <hi>Whites</hi>) could not proceed from any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, becauſe when Animals are Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally Black, they do not Procreate conſtantly Black ones (as the <hi>Negroes</hi> do) as in Dogs, Cows, Sheep, and in ſome Birds; Accidental Colours vary in the ſame Numerical Subject by changes of Seaſons, of Diet, of Culture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but a <hi>Negro</hi> will always be a <hi>Negro,</hi> carry him to <hi>Greenland,</hi> give him Chalk, Feed and Manage him never ſo many ways.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantia Semina Rerum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="essay">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96000:19"/>
            <head>THE SECOND ESSAY, CONCERNING The Riſe, Progreſs, and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Fables and Romances. With the State of Learning.</head>
            <p>THE bare, naked, or ſimple way of Inſtructing by Precept, being found jejune and nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, a mixture of <hi>Fable</hi> was therefore thought neceſſary to ſweeten and allure the minds of men, naturally Superſtitious and Credulous; which kind of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> was firſt made uſe of amongſt the <hi>Eaſtern Nations,</hi> the <hi>Hebrews</hi> themſelves not excepted. Hence 'tis that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96000:20"/>the Oldeſt Books are <hi>Mythological,</hi> as <hi>Aeſop, Homer, Heſiod, Orpheus,</hi> &amp;c. This Fabulous way of Writing paſs'd from the <hi>Poets to the Schools</hi> and <hi>Theaters. Sed diligentèr intuere has Naenias, quantam ſub illis utilitatem reperies, nec aliud quidquam per fabellas quaeritur, quam corrigatur Error ut mortalium, acuatque ſeſe diligent indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</hi> Phoedrus.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Herodotus</hi> and <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> there are many <hi>Fictions,</hi> but invented only for want of <hi>Truth;</hi> ſuch are the imaginary <hi>Originals</hi> of moſt Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the true ſort of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is judiciouſly diſtinguiſh'd by <hi>Diodorus,</hi> from the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thological</hi> or Fabulous; ſuch as is all that before the <hi>Trojan War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Strabo</hi> affirms, That the Hiſtories of the <hi>Perſians, Medes,</hi> and <hi>Syrians,</hi> deſerve little Credit; the inventors of <hi>Fables</hi> were in ſuch vogue and eſteem, that all their <hi>Writers</hi> followed the <hi>Romantick</hi> vein, which had reign'd long in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſeeds of <hi>Fiction</hi> being tranſplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>Greece,</hi> found the ſoil very fertile and luxuriant. The <hi>Greeks</hi> addicted to <hi>Poetry</hi> and <hi>Invention,</hi> ran all upon <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, Allegories, Fables,</hi> and <hi>Parables.</hi> The <hi>Egyptians</hi> before had taught them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96000:20"/>the <hi>Myſterious</hi> way under <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> under masks and diſguiſes, which make up their <hi>Mythologick Theology.</hi> The Tales told by the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts to <hi>Pythagoras, Plato,</hi> and other <hi>Greeks,</hi> fail'd not to tickle their curioſity and paſſion of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. <hi>Graecia Mendax</hi> —.</p>
            <p>The Sacred Authors themſelves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with this Humour of <hi>Parables</hi> and <hi>Fictions,</hi> the Holy Scripture being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Myſterious, Allegorical and Enigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical; and our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf gave his Precepts under this veil. The <hi>Talmud</hi> contains Millions of <hi>Fables,</hi> every one more impertinent than another. The <hi>Arabians</hi> excelled the <hi>Hebrews</hi> in Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, Similitudes, and Fictions, of which their <hi>Alcoran</hi> is a proof, as well as their numerous Troops of <hi>Poets,</hi> which afterwards infected <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> with <hi>Rhodomantade</hi> and <hi>Knight-Errantry, Giants, Dragons, Enchanted Caſtles,</hi> and ſuch like acts of <hi>Chivalry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe fountains the Chriſtian <hi>Monks</hi> drunk in the art of Lying, and compoſing of <hi>Legends;</hi> but they did not tell their <hi>Tales</hi> ſo finely as the <hi>Greeks</hi> and the <hi>Orientals.</hi> They imitate the <hi>Sibyls</hi> and the <hi>Oracles</hi> in their Cells and Hermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, though not in the Wiſdom or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96000:21"/>Cunning of their Precepts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; which yet <hi>Tully</hi> himſelf ſpoke contemptibly of. <hi>Quid verò habet Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis furor iſte, quem divinum vocamus, ut, quae ſapiens non videat, ea videat inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; Is, qui humanos ſenſus amiſerit, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinos aſſecutus ſit? Sibyllae verſus obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quos illa furens fudiſſe dicitur—.</hi> De Divinat. How long was it inculacted up and down that the <hi>Devil</hi> ſpoke in the <hi>Oracles,</hi> and that they were all ſilenced at our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s coming, till <hi>D. van Dale</hi> prov'd the contrary beyond all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie and diſpute. <hi>V. Diſſert. de Oracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Eorumque duratione &amp; Auctoribus.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">vo</hi> 
               <hi>Amſtelodam,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>I might give here an account of the famous <hi>Edda,</hi> which relates the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful atchievements of <hi>Woden</hi> and his Wife <hi>Frigga</hi> (whoſe names we ſtill retain in our <hi>Wedneſday</hi> and <hi>Friday. See Verſtegan</hi>) with the reſt of our <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Anceſtors; a <hi>Book</hi> which for Antiquity might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with <hi>Homer,</hi> and as Fabulous as the beſt.</p>
            <p>What Stories and Tales have we of <hi>Brute,</hi> of <hi>Arthur,</hi> and <hi>Merlin?</hi> every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince had their <hi>Romancers,</hi> their <hi>Strolers,</hi> and <hi>Fable-Mongers;</hi> the whole world was over-run with Lyes, and the Fictions of theſe <hi>Practitioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96000:21"/>
            <p>The <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Nations at this very day retain their old Guſt for Fabulous Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Aſtrological Cheats, Juglers, Songſters, and lying Mountebanks. They affect ſtill the old <hi>Oriental Rhodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montade,</hi> which made up the prophane Learning of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and was ſanctified even in <hi>Syria</hi> it ſelf: The <hi>Sacred Writers</hi> complying with the pulſe of the <hi>Jews,</hi> made uſe of Fictions and Parables to expreſs their Inſpirations; therefore our <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> in the Judgment of our beſt Criticks, <hi>Grotius, Father Simon, Le Clerc,</hi> &amp;c. is altogether Myſterious, Allegorical, and Enigmatical. The <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> believed that the Book of <hi>Job</hi> is no other but a <hi>Parable</hi> of the Invention of the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> the <hi>Proverbs, Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and other Holy Songs, are Poetical Works, abounding with Figures, which would ſeem bold and violent in our Writings, and which are ordinary in thoſe of that Nation. The Book of <hi>Canticles</hi> is a kind of <hi>Dramatick Poem,</hi> where the Paſſions of the Bridegroom and Spouſe are painted after a tender and touching manner. In the Book of <hi>Ruth,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96000:22"/>and in the <hi>23d.</hi> Chapter of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> there are many wanton and laſcivious expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; inſomuch that <hi>Joſeph Scaliger</hi> was wont to ſay, that his reading of <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, Catullus, Tibullus, Propertius, Ovid,</hi> and other ſuch Authors, did very much enlighten him in the Interpretation of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> in which there are many things Divinely ſaid, above the pitch of <hi>Poets</hi> or <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thought to have proceeded with <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies</hi> and <hi>Prophecies,</hi> and with a Hiſtory of <hi>Enthuſiaſm;</hi> but I find Dr. <hi>Spencer,</hi> the late Maſter of <hi>Bennet College</hi> in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> has ſo ingeniouſly and fully handled the firſt, and <hi>Meric Caſaubon</hi> the latter, that a <hi>Genius</hi> much higher than mine will ſcarcely attempt to come after them. I will only remark here once for all, That men in former days that knew and performed above the ordinary level, were ſuſpected of <hi>Magick;</hi> and therefore the Learned <hi>Naudaeus</hi> wrote an <hi>Apology</hi> for all the Wiſe Men who have unjuſtly been reputed <hi>Magicians,</hi> from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the preſent Age; and indeed it is to be wiſh'd that ſome Able Pen would do the like for the many <hi>Sagacious Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96000:22"/>who are at this day moſt inhumanly accus'd of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> becauſe they ſearch, and find, and hunt a little out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon field, or do not run headlong in the high road.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peſſima res eſt errorum Apotheoſis, &amp; pro peſte intellectus habenda eſt, ſi va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis accedat Veneratio.</hi> Bacon. Nov. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tam magna penuria Mentis ubique,</l>
               <l>In nugas tam prona Via eſt —</l>
               <l>Et ſic Obſervatio creſcit</l>
               <l>Ex Atavis quondam male caepta, deinde ſequutis</l>
               <l>Tradita temporibus, ſeriſque Nepotibus aucta.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prudent. in Symach.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>To this <hi>Eſſay</hi> of Fables and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, the Hiſtory of <hi>Daemonology</hi> doth properly belong, with all the terrible troops of <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Witches;</hi> but I find this Part is ſo Judiciouſly and Learnedly Treated of by our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> in that Book of his <hi>Leviathan,</hi> called the <hi>Kingdom of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and lately by Dr. <hi>Becker</hi> of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96000:23"/>in Four Tomes,</hi> called <hi>Le Monde Enchanteé,</hi> that my labour will be all loſt, and would only prove dull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition; therefore I haſten to the end and deſtruction of them in theſe <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts of the World, by what ſteps it was brought on, and how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily finiſhed.</p>
            <p>The moſt early ſtrokes, we meet with, are in <hi>Dante, Petrach,</hi> and <hi>Boccace,</hi> in <hi>Chaucer,</hi> and <hi>Wiclef;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the taking of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> the exil'd <hi>Grecians</hi> fled into <hi>Italy,</hi> where under the wings of <hi>Lorenzo de Medici,</hi> ſound Learning and good Senſe began to hatch and creep abroad, foſter'd and fed by that <hi>Illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> cultivated by thoſe excellent Wits, <hi>Poggius, Aretinus, Valla, Gaza, Hermolaus Barbarus, Angelus Politia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and others, who flouriſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 1400 and 1500.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Art of Printing</hi> being invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about 1442, and ſpread up and down <hi>Europe</hi> by 1480 and 1490, and aſterwards improved and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to perfection from 1500 to 1600,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96000:23"/>under the care and exquiſite Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Aldi,</hi> the <hi>Stephani,</hi> the <hi>Frobenij, Commelin, Plantine,</hi> and others; the Rays of new <hi>Light</hi> began to dart abroad, and our <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> to be all Illuminated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reuchlin, Eraſmus, Palingenius, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanan,</hi> &amp;c. diſpell'd the Miſts of <hi>Monkery,</hi> and a ſort of <hi>Reformation</hi> appeared in glimmerings and flaſhes.</p>
            <p>The mighty <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſprung up about this time, and with his <hi>Royal</hi> cloak covered the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Muſes:</hi> Hobgoblins and Phantomes fled at the riſing of this Star, which ſoon grew up to be the Sun and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Letters,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the <hi>Patron</hi> of Arts and Sciences; in his Reign we read of the <hi>Bellay</hi>'s, the <hi>Chaſtel</hi>'s, <hi>Budaeus, Rabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais, Julius Scaliger, Gyllius, Bellonius, Geſner, Rondeletius,</hi> and many other Eminent Men, who carried Learning up to a great height.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of this laſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, <hi>England</hi> had the Honour and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96000:24"/>Felicity to produce my <hi>Lord Bacon,</hi> a Man of wonderful Invention and Fertility in vaſt Deſigns; he ſaw the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> had ſpun <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> to its utmoſt Fineneſs and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which laid buried many Ages under <hi>Gothick Ruins</hi> and <hi>Monkiſh Rubbiſh;</hi> he ſaw the Reſtoration of this <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Civility</hi> and <hi>Politeneſs,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the <hi>Belle Lettre</hi> to reaſſume its utmoſt ſtrength in <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon;</hi> therefore he drew another <hi>Plan,</hi> and laid the foundation of a <hi>New Experimental Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon the Obſervations of Senſe and Matter of Fact; which hath been ſince proſecuted in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> the <hi>Mechanicks, Natural</hi> and <hi>Phyſical Hiſtory,</hi> with a happy ſucceſs in moſt parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> 'Tis therefore that the preſent <hi>Age</hi> affords ſo much of real Knowledge, and will not endure empty Notions, and vain Speculations, which had ſo long amus'd and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poured the <hi>World:</hi> We preſently call for clear Proof, Fact, or ocular De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration: What Improvements in all the parts of Life might not be expected from ſuch ſound <hi>Principles,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96000:24"/>if we had a <hi>Richelieu</hi> or a <hi>Colbert</hi> to put the Springs and Wheels in motion? For want of ſuch a fund, the <hi>True Philoſophy</hi> begins to degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and dwindle into <hi>Goſſiping,</hi> into <hi>Tale-telling,</hi> into <hi>Jeſts,</hi> into <hi>Romantick Hypotheſes,</hi> and idle <hi>Whimſies: Nubes pro Junone.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96000:25"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Thought to have troubled Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> no further at preſent, my Temper diſpoſing me to ſpeak little, and write ſhort; but obſerving in many late <hi>Authors</hi> a falſe method of making gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Univerſal Concluſions from ſome Particulars, I could not but take notice of it in this place, becauſe Your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> has a true Logical Head, and a ſound way of Reaſoning.</p>
            <p>Some <hi>Writers,</hi> becauſe they find <hi>Shells</hi> on the Shoars, to be the Spoils or <hi>Exuviae</hi> of Sea-Animals, and Plants at Land to riſe from Seed; therefore they conclude, That all other Shells, or Shell-ſtones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling them, muſt come from the ſame place, and all Vegetables be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the ſame manner; ſo they affirm all <hi>Inſects</hi> to be Generated by <hi>Animal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96000:25"/>becauſe they obſerve ſome to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from <hi>Eggs;</hi> as though <hi>Nature,</hi> or the <hi>Almightier Governor</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> muſt be confined in all the various myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ways of <hi>Generation,</hi> to their ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or narrow Caprice, founded upon a few particular Obſervations.</p>
            <p>Many Cruſtaceous and Teſtaceous Animals are peculiar to Lakes, Rivers, Thickets, Caves, Rocks, Beds of Mud and Sand, of which many <hi>Species</hi> are unknown to us at this day; and perhaps the Land, or Freſh-water Shells may be as numerous as thoſe at Sea; therefore we need not fetch all our Subterrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Shell-Stones</hi> from the Ocean; but I ſee no Contradiction or Abſurdity in <hi>Nature</hi> in aſcribing the Origine of <hi>Theſe</hi> reſembling Marine Shells, to the <hi>Plaſtick Power</hi> (or call it what <hi>Principle</hi> you pleaſe) of the Earth; the ſame may be ſaid of the <hi>Subterraneous Vegetables;</hi> for this way of explicating theſe <hi>Appearances</hi> is not attended with half ſo many or great difficulties, as that of bringing them in by an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Diſſolution of the Earth at the Deluge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shells, or Teſtaceous figured Bodies, may be Generated in Beds of Earth, or Stone, as eaſily as Animals or Plants
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96000:26"/>themſelves, which are ſometimes found alive upon the breaking of Rocks and Stones aſunder, into which neither Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor Air, nor Animal Parent, nor Ieed could have any ingreſs; eſpecially if we ſuppoſe with <hi>the late Author of the Eſſay towards a Natural Hiſtory of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. that Quarries, or the <hi>Strata</hi> of Stone, were formed upon the Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Globe,</hi> when diſſevered and taken all to pieces in the <hi>Flood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men converſant in Medical Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Anatomical Hiſtory, obſerve great variety of Stones curiouſly Figured and Coloured, as alſo wonderful diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Worms and other Inſects, to be daily formed in the Bodies of Animals, eſpecially in the Gall, Bladders, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs, and Glands; but they meet with inſuperable difficulties when they attempt to bring them into the <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm</hi> they know not what ways, nor from what places. So the <hi>Subterraneous Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culators</hi> viewing Teſtaceous and other Animal and Vegetable-like Bodies in the Bowels of the <hi>greater world</hi> are forc'd upon the rack when they endeavour to fetch 'em in from ſtrange places. The ſafeſt way is to take the neareſt cauſe, and to expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>Nature</hi> by her immediate ſteps and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96000:26"/>appearances; as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> did very judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly upon this occaſion: <hi>Teſtacea inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùm ſpontè è limo proveniunt, alia ex alio; oſtreae in coenoſo, conchae &amp; quae ſuprà dixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Sabuloſo; circa Saxorum cava Papillae ſeu Tethya, Balani ſeu Glandes, &amp; quae per ſumma adhaerent, ut Lepades ſeu Patellae, &amp; Neritae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither are <hi>Shell-like Bodies</hi> ſometimes thus Propagated, but <hi>Vegetables</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which will often ſpring up plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully in Countries where they never grew before, even out of the Trunks of Trees, out of Stones, and on the tops of the higheſt places. What <hi>Myriads of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects</hi> are produced upon Steeping <hi>Pepper</hi> in Rain water? And ſhall we wonder to ſee <hi>Shell-ſtones,</hi> Teeth, and other <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like figured Bodies</hi> in the Bowels of the Earth, when we find the ſame, if not greater, Wonders in our own <hi>Bodies,</hi> and in thoſe of <hi>Quadrupeds, Birds,</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes;</hi> as <hi>Teeth in Abſceſſes, perfect Shells in Glands, Bezoar in Stomachs, Teſtaceous</hi> or <hi>Laminated ſtones</hi> in the internal parts of <hi>Cruſtaceous</hi> and <hi>Finned Fiſhes,</hi> as alſo In <hi>naked Snails,</hi> beſides curious varieties of <hi>Inſects</hi> in many parts of moſt Animals? Of which Phyſical Cauſes may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, without taking the <hi>Microcoſm</hi> all
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96000:27"/>to pieces in order to bring them in, <hi>vi &amp; Armis,</hi> by diſſolving all that ſtands in their way.</p>
            <p>'Tis hard to conceive how ſuch innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable <hi>Aquatick Animals</hi> ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by a <hi>Deluge</hi> of their own <hi>Element;</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> knew better things, <hi>Animalia, quae in Aquis vivere poſſunt, Diluvij plaga non tetigit, haec enim terrena tantùm morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficavit;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> inflicted this puniſhment only upon the <hi>Earth</hi> and its <hi>Creatures,</hi> Why ſo many Millions of <hi>Fiſhes Bones</hi> and <hi>Integuments</hi> to be entomb'd in Graves or Beds, perhaps a 1000 Miles below the ſurface of the Earth, under Layers of Stones and Marble, where they are ſaid to fall or ſink by their <hi>ſpecifick Gravity,</hi> during the <hi>General Diſſolution of the Earth by the Deluge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeems to be of a different Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the <hi>Writer of the late Eſſay</hi> (tho he pretends to corroborate and ſupport <hi>the Moſaic Syſtem</hi>) for <hi>Moſes</hi> gives a plain and clear Relation of the Mountains ſtanding firm and entire during the whole Scene of that Action; read the <hi>7th.</hi> and <hi>8th. Chapter</hi> of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> and if the Hills continued in their Antidiluvian ſtate, I do not ſee how ſo many Millions of <hi>Shells, Teeth,</hi> and other <hi>Bones</hi> of <hi>Sea-Animals,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96000:27"/>together with ſuch numbers of <hi>Antidiluvian Vegetables,</hi> could poſſibly be buried ſo deep in the <hi>Entrails</hi> of our <hi>Planet,</hi> fortified and encompaſſed with <hi>Arches</hi> of <hi>Metallick Mines</hi> and <hi>Quarries.</hi> If the <hi>Ocean</hi> did overflow the whole <hi>Globe</hi> (againſt which many Batteries have been rais'd by the greateſt Scholars of this Iſland, <hi>Iſaac Voſſius</hi> and the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Learned Biſhop of Worceſter</hi>) and brought along with it many Marine Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies out of their natural Site or Beds; then 'tis probable that the ſame fluid <hi>Principle,</hi> or <hi>Maſs,</hi> might have rouled them back again from whence it had driven them; for the Sea is ſaid to return to its primaeval Channel immediately after the work was over, ſo it might have carried them back again as eaſily as it rouz'd them at firſt from their native Depths, or Marine Scituations.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Narborough</hi> in his Voyage to <hi>Chili,</hi> obſerv'd in ſeveral Cliffs and Hills on the Coaſts of <hi>Patagonia,</hi> lumps of <hi>Oyſter Shells</hi> buried up and down at Land; yet he could never find any <hi>Oyſters</hi> in thoſe Seas, though he had Sounded moſt of the <hi>Ports</hi> of <hi>Southern America.</hi> Every body knows that this <hi>Shell-Fiſh</hi> always breeds near the Shoars;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96000:28"/>ſo that flying to the deep can be no ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge here.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Europe</hi> many <hi>ſhell-ſtones,</hi> or <hi>Foſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil ſhells,</hi> as alſo <hi>ſubterraneous Vegetables</hi> are found, which are not to be match'd either at Sea or Land; to fancy them in dark and remote Parts of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> ſeems but a weak evaſion; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome may be ſampled at Sea, therefore all muſt come from thence, is not a very ſound Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Several <hi>Authors</hi> have attempted to prove the <hi>Strata,</hi> or Layers of our <hi>Globe,</hi> to proceed from the ſeveral <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Deluge;</hi> and that the <hi>Lapis Judaicus,</hi> the <hi>Aſtroites,</hi> or <hi>Star-ſtone Columns</hi> (of which there are ſome of enormous Dimenſions) the <hi>Bufonites</hi> or <hi>Toadſtone,</hi> the <hi>Gloſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrae,</hi> and <hi>Cornua Ammonis</hi> (though nothing like it at Sea) are really the Teeth, Spines, Bones, and other parts of <hi>Sea-Animals,</hi> left behind in the Bowels of the Earth by the <hi>General Flood.</hi> But, I think, all theſe <hi>Ingenious Writers</hi> have ſtronger Fancies than Judgments, and a meaner Opinion of the Invention, Art, and Power of <hi>Nature,</hi> then ſhe deſerves; for any
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96000:28"/>common <hi>Obſerver</hi> muſt find <hi>Her</hi> to vary and ſport in nothing ſo much as in the Figures, Textures, Shootings, and Growths of <hi>Foſſils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The common Problem, That a Solid included within a Solid, muſt of neceſſity pre-exiſt before the external or including Solid, is notoriouſly falſe from the daily Generation of new Solids and new Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals (as Ferrugineous and Teſtaceous Stones, as alſo various Inſects) within the Solid parts of ſeveral Bodies: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth this neceſſarily induce any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitous or aequivocal Generation, though the latter may, perhaps, ſometimes be brought about in the imperfect kinds of Animals, by the ſame power that intends over and governs the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nivocal Generation</hi> of Inſects; for that <hi>Powerful Principle</hi> is not limited to one ſingle plaſtick Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, ſeeing Matter is capable of all Forms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jovis Omnia plena.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
